Guide to the Andrew St. George Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Original inventory, Accession 2010-M-036
  - Photographs
    - Cuba
      - Sierra Maestra, 1957-1958 (Box 8, Folder 2)
        These prints were largely made from photographs taken during St. George's last visit to Cuba before the fall of Batista for an article or series of articles he expected to title "Behind Rebel Lines." The fall of Batista clearly changed that. The photographs show: a rebel officer taking an inventory of requisitioned goods in a company store; an elderly man sifting corn; rebels and locals socializing at a bar or cantina in a rural town; a group of rebel soldiers standing in conversation (the tallest among them, smoking a cigar, is a veteran of the Spanish Civil War shown in other photographs as he makes bombs in a rebel bomb shop); a rebel with a gun at a lookout post near the national shrine to the Virgin of Charity, known in Cuba as la Virgen del Cobre, in Cobre, Oriente; a large number of armed rebels marching through a small rural town; same group of rebels as they come over a hillside; young man adjusting a shortwave radio with two men wearing 26th of July beréts next to him; rebel loading an anti-aircraft gun on tripod loaded with a small homemade missile-shaped projectile; rebels working on a requisitioned jeep; blond officer Manuel Boronat overseeing the drying of coffee beans in the sun; composite and retouched print showing unknown rebel, Che Guevara, Universo Sánchez, Raúl and Fidel Castro, Crescencio Pérez and St. George (an uncropped version of this photograph is in box 7, folder 2); nocturnal image of a rebel walking away from what looks like a small building that has been set ablaze (St. George describes this building as a munitions dump in his 1970 oral presentation at Yale narrating filmed out-takes that include this scene). Additional photographs show a dark-toned peasant wearing a hat, sitting or standing before a map of the province with a draped flag and portrait of Castro; rebels in a requisitioned car looking out the window on the driver's side; bearded, shirtless rebel wearing gold Catholic medal as he stands inside an open-air kitchen with another rebel looking on; man exhaling smoke, possibly as part of a typical cleansing ritual; seven hammocks hanging from the ceiling of a thatched-roof building (one clearly occupied); rebel with rifle fleeing from an unidentified construction that has been set ablaze; several men, probably from the 26th of July urban underground, standing on the rocky shore in the company of rebel soldiers as all eleven presumably awaiting transportation to another part of the island (several look out into the distance using binoculars with some bearded men carrying guns); rebel scout or messenger leading a donkey on the hillside; 18 rebels, many with guns aimed in the direction of the camera, posing atop a large military jeep that probably belonged to Raúl Castro's column.
      - Enma Castro's wedding, 1959 April (Box 8, Folder 3)
        These prints include scenes from Enma Castro's wedding in April 1959. One print shows Fidel Castro standing near the bride and groom inside the church as he is checking his watch. In this photo, President Osvaldo Dorticós stands to Castro's immediate left; on Castro's right are Raúl Castro and Vilma Espín (wearing lace veil over her head in the Catholic style). Two additional photos of the wedding ceremony include important members of the Castro family: in one, Enma and her Mexican bridegroom kneel before the altar as Ramón Castro, the eldest of the 3 Castro brothers, looks on. In a second picture, as Enma and the bridegroom prepare to take their vows, her future mother-in-law and her mother, Lina Ruz González, stand to Enma's immediate left. This folder includes an interesting shot of the mammoth crowd, mostly composed of women, outside the Cathedral of Havana as they press on the limousine with the recently married couple inside (not visible).
      - Counter-revolutionary sabotage and violence; documentation of Cuban military's increasing control over all aspects of society, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 4)
        These photographs document the militarization of Cuba in response to counter-revolutionary violence in 1959, and as a result of continuing counter-revolutionary attacks in 1960, the Revolution's own increasing reliance on authoritarian tactics to intimidate and repress critics. Three of these photographs had captions originally glued to the verso side of the prints. The caption to one photograph (stamped 3-30-1960), shot at the gates of Camp Columbia (renamed Camp Libertad after the fall of Batista), reads: "II: MILITARY FEVER GRIPS CUBA. With the military extending their jurisdiction over all phases of Cuban national life, their rule grows harsher and narrower. Here a group of Cuban newsmen are awaiting in front of main gate to Camp Libertad—the principal military post of the Cuban army—to cover a trial of some alleged counterrevolutionaries, conducted by military judges before a closed court martial. Newsmen waited all day, but trial remains closed." The second print, stamped 10-29-1959 for Life Magazine, includes this caption on the back: "Habana, Oct 26, 1959: Violence in Cuba: Harness cops and plain clothesmen swarm around hole in glass pane of front door to editorial offices of Revolución, Fidel Castro's own Habana newspaper; minutes earlier, unidentified terrorists had tossed a handgrenade [sic] through hole, which wounded three people." A third print shows men undressing with their backs to the camera. It is captioned as follows: "With all Cubans of both sexes between ages of 6 and 60 eligible for milicia duty and with new anti-Castro guerrilla forces fighting in the mountains of the Sierra Maestra (in background) all Cuba is getting into uniform, like these shivering and reluctant milicianos of the Havana Architects and Lawyers Militia Battalion; they are called to duty to defend the government against anti-Castro 'bandits' and against a 'foreign invasion.' This photo was taken in brand-new militia camp at Las Mercedes, among Sierra Maestra foothills." A copy of this photograph is in Box 43, folder 14. Lillian Guerra noted "there were never any anti-Castro guerrilla operating in the Sierra Maestra, during 1960 when this picture was taken or after. Rather, the movement was located in El Escambray and between 1960 and 1965, the government labeled its members "bandits" in order to discredit them." Other prints show a prisoner being led away by two members of Cuban intelligence, most probably at the former Marista School in Havana that became an interrogation and holding center for political prisoners in 1960; a wrecked eighteen-wheel truck loaded with eggs that ran off the road (probably by act of counter-revolutionary sabotage), January 1960; military vehicles covered in tarps as seen through the window of a car (image stamped 1961); a downed plane on the national highway surrounded by a curious crowd and militia men (undated but likely 1960); two shots of snipers posted at the top of the control tower of Havana's international airport (winter 1960); troops riding atop tanks during a military parade (probably May 1, 1960, at the Plaza of the Revolution); three members of the army, two of whom sit on a couch (one reading a comic, the other a political education manual issued to the army); and finally, a scene of a woman near two parked cars, one of which shows a sign that reads (in Spanish): "The planes left from the United States." This sign references the aerial fly-bys and leafletting campaign that the former head of the Cuban Revolutionary Air Force, Pedro Díaz Lanz, carried out in October 1959 around the same time as the Huber Matos affair and attending national crisis over the disappearance (and presumed assassination) of Camilo Cienfuegos.
      - Student protest of Anastas Mikoyan's state visit to Cuba, 1960 February (Box 8, Folder 5)
        These photographs center on a Catholic Students' Association rally in Central Park, Havana, around the statue of José Martí. One photograph shows a boy speaking into a microphone from a speaker's dais as a white robed priest stands next to it. The boy is wearing a small badge that reads (in Spanish) "Day of the Catholic Student" on his lapel. The second photograph shows a group of priests and seminarians standing with three students on the outskirts of the crowd, just in front and to the side of the statue of Martí.
      - Fidel Castro's visit to Venezuela, 1959 January (Box 8, Folder 6)
        These photographs document Fidel Castro's January 23, 1959 trip to Caracas, Venezuela, which celebrated the anniversary of the fall of the former Venezuelan dictator exactly one year to the day earlier, and the establishment of the democratic government of Romulo Betancourt with whom Castro met. Five photographs in this group show Fidel sitting next to Betancourt at a luncheon table with various members of Fidel's personal body guard unit immediately behind. Betancourt is the portly, balding man in the tie sitting next to him.
      - Fidel visits United Nations and stays at Hotel Theresa in Harlem, 1960 September (Box 8, Folder 7)
        This folder contains eight pictures from Fidel's September 1960 trip to New York City to speak at the United Nations. Included are seven photographs taken during his stay at Harlem's Hotel Theresa and one of a demonstration against Castro where protesters stood behind a barricade holding a large poster image of image of Camilo Cienfuegos and signs comparing Fidel to Hitler. In the foreground, next to a shouting demonstrator wearing a hand-painted T-shirt reading 'Cuba SI' (in English, Cuba Yes) is Luis Conte Agüero. Conte Agüero had been Castro's close friend and informal public relations manager during his imprisonment on the Isle of Pines under Batista from 1953 to 1955. Conte Agüero left Cuba in 1960; at the time, he was a journalist and television personality. An identical photograph is in Box 43, folder 3. There is an additional print from NBC's Meet the Press show on April 19, 1959, during Castro's first visit to the United States. Shown are Ned Brooks, moderator for the show; Castro; and Anthony Hervas, interpreter. An identical photograph is in Box 43, folder 2.
      - Carnival and tourist sites for story on honeymooning couple (the Minoffs) and decline of U. S. tourism, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 8)
        All of these photographs were taken when St. George visited Cuba during Carnival season for a story on the collapse of foreign tourism to Cuba. For this story, he accompanied Marvin and Phyllis Miroff, a honeymooning American couple, whom he photographed as they ate in El Floridita, an abandoned restaurant at the entrance to Obispo Street, near Havana's Central Park. Two prints show members of a comparsa dancing on El Prado, a street in front of the Capitol Building in Centro Habana. Three photographs show women dressed in costume and parading or dancing as they perform in different nightclub settings. An additional two photographs show a Cuban Chinese dance troupe performing on El Prado, adjacent to the building that housed the soon-to-be-defunct Diario de la Marina, Cuba's oldest and most conservative newspaper. There are two identical photographic portraits of an unidentified, corpulent Cuban woman wearing sparkly clothing and earrings. There are four photographs of the casino at the Hotel Riviera, one of the last hotels built under Batista. These hotels were built largely by and for the U.S. mafia, which used them to launder money and run a narco-trafficking operation. On the back of one these casino images St. George wrote "Havana Riviera casino, of which Masferrer was part owner." The caption refers to Rolando Masferrer, the head of one of Batista's bloodiest and most notorious death squads, known as Los Tigres, which operated in Holguin, Oriente. Masferrer was forced to flee the country in November 1959 mostly after bad press coverage on his excesses led the United States to pressure Batista into limiting Masferrer's activities. Finally, there is one print, also taken during this February 1960 assignment, of three small boys watching the scene inside a bar in Old Havana at night. These boys are shown in many different shots contained in the Cuban Revolution Collection (MS 650 http://hdl.handle.net/10079/fa/mssa.ms.0650).
      - U.S. arms dealer known as "The Black Eagle," taken at Hotel Nacional and unidentified hotel, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 9)
        These photographs depict Col. F. Julian, a U.S. arms dealer known as "The Black Eagle." In one photograph he is standing with an unidentified blond tourist from Virginia at the counter of the Hotel Nacional; the other shows him engaged in conversation with a man who appears to be St. George as they sit together in a hotel room.
      - Trial of two American agents of CIA, convicted of fomenting counter-revolution, 1959 November (Box 8, Folder 10)
        These photographs were taken at the trial of Peter Lambton and Austin Young, two Central Intelligence Agency agents captured in Pinar del Río province in the fall of 1959. Local peasants denounced them as attempting to foment a counter-revolutionary guerrilla movement against the government. More detailed information about the trial of Lambton and Young can be found in the Cuban Revolution Collection (MS 650; http://hdl.handle.net/10079/fa/mssa.ms.0650); see Contact Book VI, Prints 1-7, Revolutionary Tribunal Trial of two United States Fighter Pilots.
      - Fidel's tour of northeast United States; photographs of televised interview and press conference, 1959 April (Box 8, Folder 11)
        Four close up shots of Fidel Castro speaking with a reporter in a televised interview taped in the United States during Castro's April 1959 visit. Castro is also seen at a press conference, most likely in the United States, with his then translator, Teresa Casuso, at his side.
      - Street demonstrations to support the Cuban government, 1959 October (Box 8, Folder 12)
        These photos depict pro-government demonstrations protesting counter-revolutionary violence by Cuban exiles based in the United States. As is clear from the garlands on lamp posts saying "Welcome ASTA" [American Society of Travel Agents] in English, these photographs were taken in October 1959 when Cuba hosted America's largest association of travel agents. One photo, showing female protestors in the foreground and a truck filled with militia members, was taken near the street known as La Rampa in the Vedado neighborhood of Havana. Another shows demonstrators staging a road block along Havana's sea wall, known as El Malecón. Two additional photographs show a group of demonstrators and a group of men running down Reina Street, near the corner with Carlos III.
      - Spanish Civil War veteran Alberto Bayo, Circa 1959 (Box 8, Folder 13)
        These prints show Spanish Civil War veteran Alberto Bayo who provided training in guerrilla warfare to Che Guevara and other members of Castro's group during their 1955 exile in Mexico. Bayo is shown seated in two duplicate images and then standing on the street waiting for his female companion to get into or out of a car; in this picture, a series of armed bodyguards surround Bayo.
      - U. S. Ambassador Philip Bonsal with Fidel and in various locations, 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 14)
        All of these prints depict Philip W. Bonsal, US Ambassador to Cuba from 1959 to 1960. Bonsal is shown in three photographs in the company of his wife and other members of the embassy staff as they prepare to board a flight at the Havana airport. Two other images show Bonsal on the day he presented his credentials to the Cuban revolutionary government in early 1959 at the Presidential Palace. In one of these, he descends the staircase, and in the second, he stands at the main entrance on El Prado. Other photographs show him in the back seat of a car and at his only meeting with Fidel Castro; this latter one is part of a series of shots that are in Box 7, folder 13. There are also two contact sheets and accompanying negatives of images of Bonsal having cocktails with two other Americans, the oil refinery in Havana harbor, and members of a delegation from Communist China.
      - Ramón Castro, Raúl Chibas and William Morgan, 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 15)
        Included are three unusual photographs portraying important leaders of the revolutionary war against Batista and Fidel's often forgotten older brother, Ramón Castro. Ramón is shown in a seated, formal portrait shot. The photograph with a man wearing horn-rimmed glasses and a military uniform is Raúl Chibás, a founding member of the Orthodox Party to which Fidel had once been a member. Although the location and activity are unclear, Fidel can be seen talking to uniformed members of the crew over Chibás's right shoulder, in the rear. Two additional photographs show the famous blond and blue-eyed William Morgan, an American who joined the Segundo Frente del Escambray and fought Batista in early 1958.
      - Archbishop Enrique Pérez Serantes attending a mass political rally, Circa 1959 (Box 8, Folder 16)
        These photographs are of Archbishop of Santiago de Cuba Enrique Pérez Serantes attending a mass rally. He is surrounded by people in uniform who appear to be armed members of the revolutionary militia. Pérez Serantes was most famous for having intervened in 1953 to save Fidel and Raúl Castro's lives when Batista ordered the capture and execution of all members of the commando team who attacked the Moncada Military Barracks on the 26th of July.
      - Mass rallies, 1959 January-1960 July (Box 8, Folder 17)
        These prints depict scenes from different mass rallies in support of the government held between January 1959 and July 1960. In one image, a woman who fainted from the heat of the crowd is treated by members of the Red Cross. This photograph probably dates from January 1959 with the rally in support of executing war criminals held before the Presidential Palace. Two nocturnal images show large crowd scenes. The context for one of these images can be discerned: protestors holding signs denouncing Spain's Ambassador to Cuba after a famous incident occurred on live television when Fidel accused Spain of aiding and abetting counter-revolutionaries. Spanish Ambassador Vellizca himself appeared and insulted Fidel before the cameras and denied any involvement. A large sign reads: "Vellizca, Para España o Para la Cabaña" ("Vellizca, go back to Spain or suffer the pain"). La Cabaña was the military fortress that held supporters of the Batista regime before trial and execution. Another photograph depicts Fidel in close view giving a speech at a rally, while a second photograph shows him from behind addressing a massive crowd near the Sierra Maestra on July 26, 1959. Fidel is also seen surrounded by members of the revolutionary government as he speaks from the balcony of the Presidential Palace. Immediately under Fidel's raised right arm is Efigenio Almeijras, chief of the national police, and along the front, President Osvaldo Dorticós is seen clapping with a small boy and Camilo Cienfuegos at this side. The final picture shows Fidel and others as they observe a military parade, most likely on May 1, 1960, from the base of the Monumento de José Martí in Havana's Plaza de la Revolución. In the top row, left to right, the following are identified: bearded man with dark glasses, Faustino Pérez; moustached man seated next to him, holding hat, Efigenio Almeijras; Osvlado Doricós, standing; Fidel Castro; further to the right are William Morgan (edge of image, blonde); Eloy Gutiérrez Menoyo (seated with dark glasses and very thin frame); behind both of them appears to be a laughing Jacobo Arbenz, former elected president of Guatemala who was toppled by a CIA-staged coup for supporting land reform in 1954.
      - Indonesian president Sukarno on his visit to Cuba, 1960 March (Box 8, Folder 18)
        These two photographs are of Fidel Castro and Sukarno, President of Indonesia, during the latter's March 1960 trip to Cuba. One print shows Sukarno and Fidel with others at a pig farm; a bearded Antonio Nuñez Jiménez stands next to Sukarno. The other photograph shows Sukarno holding the hands of a young girl and smiling while his luncheon companions, including Fidel Castro, smoking a cigar, and a crowd look on.
      - Carlos Prío de Socarrás, Vilma Espín and Carlos Franqui, Circa 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 19)
        There is a close up image of Carlos Prío de Socarrás, former President of Cuba who was deposed by Batista's March 1952 coup. Prío provided money for Fidel to mount his expedition to Cuba in 1956 from Mexico aboard the yacht Granma. Prío later returned twice in 1959 and 1960 to show his support for the regime. He later broke with the Revolution and committed suicide in Miami in 1973. A second picture depicts Carlos Franqui (with moustache), editor of Revolución, the organ of the 26th of July Movement as of January 1959 that later became the government's official newspaper, with unknown man at his side. A third photograph depicts Vilma Espín as she is giving a speech at a conference in Mexico City. The photograph includes a caption by St. George on the verso: "STANDING APPLAUSE FROM ELITE LEADERS OF LATIN AMERICAN LEFT interrupts speech by Vilma Espín at Inter-American Anti-Imperialist Congress, a Communist-front rally she had helped organize in Mexico City. Standing at table, l—r, are Olga Poblete of Chile, Stalin-prize winner, author and top Chilean feminist leader; the Soviet Chief Delegate, Ambassador Vladimir M. Krimenko; Former President Lázaro Cárdenas of Mexico; General Felipe Yara, a famous revolutionary leader."
      - Miscellaneous photographs of men (some identified) taken after St. George left Cuba, 1961-1967 (Box 8, Folder 20)
        These photographs relate to St. George's post-1961 support for CIA-backed counter-revolutionary activities in Cuba. Several have annotations in pencil on the back, identifying the person pictured. Two duplicate images show Max Azicri Levy, identified as "CIA-Man", with a puzzle of Che Guevara's face and recent publications about Cuba in a Montevideo hotel. Another image shows Manuel Urrutia pictured in exile in 1963; he was the first president of Cuba under the Revolution and then forced to resign by Castro in July 1959. A color snapshot print shows two men talking in front of an aircraft: the verso reads "Frank Fiorini on Rt". The photograph of passengers descending a staircase from a plane upon arrival includes the caption: "ENTERING LATIN AMERICA from Cuba, this photograph shows three Chinese labor union organizers arriving at Carrasco Airport, Montevideo, (Uruguay) in the evening of 14 May 1961, aboard a special flight of the Cuban Britannia turboprop CUT 671, known among Us newsmen in Latin America for its many special flights and political passengers as 'Castro's Redball Express.' Head of this Chinese team of 'political workers' is Kuo Mao An, secretary general of the Electrical Trades Union Federation of the Chinese People's Republic (at door of plane, in broad-brimmed hat)." Two other pictures show unidentified men, both of them Cuban in single portrait close-ups. A final picture includes two American men, with the sitting man adjusting the lens to a sniper rifle with a silencer. He aims from his place at a table that includes practice target boards and another attachable rifle.
      - Vilma Espín, Raúl and Fidel Castro, Osvaldo Dorticós, and Che Guevara, 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 21)